<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is an automatically generated file. -->
<Chapter Label="Chapter_The_main_functions">
<Heading>The main functions</Heading>

<Section Label="Chapter_The_main_functions_Section_Zassenhaus_Conjecture">
<Heading>Zassenhaus Conjecture</Heading>

  This function checks whether the Zassenhaus Conjecture ((ZC) for short, cf. Section
  <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Zassenhaus_Conjecture_and_related_questions'/>) can be proved
  using the HeLP method with the data available in GAP.
<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="OrdinaryCharacterTable|Group" Name="HeLP_ZC" />
 <Returns><K>true</K> if (ZC) can be solved using the given data, <K>false</K> otherwise
</Returns>
 <Description>
  <K>HeLP_ZC</K> checks whether the Zassenhaus Conjecture can be solved for
  the given group using the HeLP method, the Wagner test and all character data available.
  The argument of the function can be either an ordinary character table
  or a group.  In the second case it will first calculate the corresponding 
  ordinary character table.
  If the group in question is nilpotent, the Zassenhaus Conjecture holds by a result of A. Weiss and the 
  function will return <K>true</K> without performing any calculations.<P/>
  If the group is not solvable, the function will check all orders
  which are divisors of the exponent of the group. If the group is solvable, it will only check the orders
  of group elements, as there can't be any torsion units of another order.
  The function will use the ordinary table 
  and, for the primes <Math>p</Math> for which the group is not <Math>p</Math>-solvable, all <Math>p</Math>-Brauer tables which are available in GAP
  to produce as many constraints on the torsion units as possible.  Additionally, the Wagner test  
  is applied to the results, cf. Section <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Wagner_test'/>.
  In case the information
  suffices to obtain a proof for the Zassenhaus Conjecture for this group
  the function will return <K>true</K> and <K>false</K> otherwise.
  The possible partial augmentations for elements of order <M>k</M> 
  and all its powers will also be stored in the list entry <K>HeLP_sol[k]</K>.<P/>
  The prior computed partial augmentations in <K>HeLP_sol</K> will not be used and will be overwritten.
  If you do not like the last fact, please use <Ref Func='HeLP_AllOrders'/>. 
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<#Include Label="ZCExample">

</Section>


<Section Label="Chapter_The_main_functions_Section_Prime_Graph_Question">
<Heading>Prime Graph Question</Heading>

  This function checks whether the Prime Graph Question ((PQ) for short, cf. Section 
  <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Zassenhaus_Conjecture_and_related_questions'/>) can be verified
  using the HeLP method with the data available in GAP.
<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="OrdinaryCharacterTable|Group" Name="HeLP_PQ" />
 <Returns><K>true</K> if (PQ) can be solved using the given data, <K>false</K> otherwise
</Returns>
 <Description>
  <K>HeLP_PQ</K> checks whether an affirmative answer for the Prime Graph Question for
  the given group can be obtained using the HeLP method, the Wagner restrictions and the data available.
  The argument of the function can be either an ordinary character table
  or a group.  In the second case it will first calculate the corresponding 
  ordinary character table.
  If the group in question is solvable, the Prime Graph Question has an affirmative answer by a result of W. Kimmerle and the 
  function will return <K>true</K> without performing any calculations.<P/>
  If the group is non-solvable, the ordinary character table and all <Math>p</Math>-Brauer
  tables for primes <Math>p</Math> for which the group is not <Math>p</Math>-solvable and which are available in GAP will be used to produce as many
  constraints on the torsion units as possible. Additionally, the Wagner test  
  is applied to the results, cf. Section <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Wagner_test'/>.
  In case the information
  suffices to obtain an affirmative answer for the Prime Graph Question,
  the function will return <K>true</K> and it will return <K>false</K> otherwise.
  Let <Math>p</Math> and <Math>q</Math> be distinct primes such that there are elements of order <Math>p</Math> and <Math>q</Math> in <Math>G</Math> but no elements of order <Math>pq</Math>.
  Then for <Math>k</Math> being <Math>p</Math>, <Math>q</Math> or <Math>pq</Math> the function will save the possible partial augmentations for elements of order <Math>k</Math>
  and its (non-trivial) powers in <K>HeLP_sol[k]</K>. The function also does not use the previously computed partial augmentations
  for elements of these orders but will overwrite the content of <K>HeLP_sol</K>.
  If you do not like the last fact, please use <Ref Func='HeLP_AllOrdersPQ'/>. 
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<#Include Label="PQExample">

</Section>


<Section Label="Chapter_The_main_functions_Section_Spectrum_Problem">
<Heading>Spectrum Problem</Heading>

  This function checks whether the Spectrum Problem ((SP) for short, cf. Section 
  <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Zassenhaus_Conjecture_and_related_questions'/>) can be verified
  using the HeLP method with the data available in GAP.
<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="OrdinaryCharacterTable|Group" Name="HeLP_SP" />
 <Returns><K>true</K> if (SP) can be solved using the given data, <K>false</K> otherwise
</Returns>
 <Description>
  <K>HeLP_SP</K> checks whether an affirmative answer for the Spectrum Problem for
  the given group can be obtained using the HeLP method, the Wagner restrictions and the data available.
  The argument of the function can be either an ordinary character table
  or a group.  In the second case it will first calculate the corresponding 
  ordinary character table.
  If the group in question is solvable, the Spectrum Problem has an affirmative answer by a result of M. Hertweck and the 
  function will return <K>true</K> without performing any calculations.<P/>
  If the group is non-solvable, the ordinary character table and all <Math>p</Math>-Brauer
  tables for primes <Math>p</Math> for which the group is not <Math>p</Math>-solvable and which are available in GAP will be used to produce as many
  constraints on the torsion units as possible. Additionally, the Wagner test  
  is applied to the results, cf. Section <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Wagner_test'/>.
  In case the information
  suffices to obtain an affirmative answer for the Spectrum Problem,
  the function will return <K>true</K> and it will return <K>false</K> otherwise.
  The possible partial augmentations for elements of order <M>k</M> 
  and all its powers will also be stored in the list entry <K>HeLP_sol[k]</K>.<P/>
  The function also does not use the previously computed partial augmentations
  for elements of these orders but will overwrite the content of <K>HeLP_sol</K>.
  If you do not like the last fact, please use <Ref Func='HeLP_AllOrdersSP'/>. 
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<#Include Label="SPExample">

</Section>


<Section Label="Chapter_The_main_functions_Section_Kimmerle_Problem">
<Heading>Kimmerle Problem</Heading>

  This function checks whether the Kimmerle Problem ((KP) for short, cf. Section 
  <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Zassenhaus_Conjecture_and_related_questions'/>) can be verified
  using the HeLP method with the data available in GAP.
<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="OrdinaryCharacterTable|Group" Name="HeLP_KP" />
 <Returns><K>true</K> if (KP) can be solved using the given data, <K>false</K> otherwise
</Returns>
 <Description>
  <K>HeLP_KP</K> checks whether an affirmative answer for the Kimmerle Problem for
  the given group can be obtained using the HeLP method, the Wagner restrictions and the data available.
  The argument of the function can be either an ordinary character table
  or a group.  In the second case it will first calculate the corresponding 
  ordinary character table.
  If the group in question is nilpotent, then even the Zassenahus Conjecture and so also the Kimmerle Problem has an affirmative answer by a result of Al Weiss and the 
  function will return <K>true</K> without performing any calculations.<P/>
  If the group is non-nilpotent, the ordinary character table and all <Math>p</Math>-Brauer
  tables for primes <Math>p</Math> for which the group is not <Math>p</Math>-solvable and which are available in GAP will be used to produce as many
  constraints on the torsion units as possible. Additionally, the Wagner test  
  is applied to the results, cf. Section <Ref Sect='Chapter_Background_Section_The_Wagner_test'/>.
  In case the information
  suffices to obtain an affirmative answer for the Kimmerle Problem,
  the function will return <K>true</K> and it will return <K>false</K> otherwise.
  The possible partial augmentations for elements of order <M>k</M> 
  and all its powers will also be stored in the list entry <K>HeLP_sol[k]</K>.<P/>
  The function also does not use the previously computed partial augmentations
  for elements of these orders but will overwrite the content of <K>HeLP_sol</K>.
  If you do not like the last fact, please use <Ref Func='HeLP_AllOrdersKP'/>. 
 </Description>
</ManSection>


<#Include Label="KPExample">

</Section>


</Chapter>

