<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is an automatically generated file. -->
<Chapter Label="Chapter_Majorana_representations">
<Heading>Majorana representations</Heading>

<Section Label="Chapter_Majorana_representations_Section_The_main_function">
<Heading>The main function</Heading>

<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="input, index, [options]" Name="MajoranaRepresentation" />
 <Returns>a record giving a Majorana representation
</Returns>
 <Description>
This takes two or three arguments, the first of which must be
 the output of the function <Ref Func="ShapesOfMajoranaRepresentation"/> and
 the second of which is the index of the desired shape in list <A>input.shapes</A>.
<P/>
 If the optional argument <A>options</A> is given then it must be a record.
 The following components of <A>options</A> are recognised:
 <List>
  <Mark><C>axioms</C></Mark>
  <Item> This component must be bound to the string <A>"AllAxioms"</A> or
  <A>"NoAxioms"</A>. If bound to <A>"AllAxioms"</A> then the algorithm assumes the axioms
  2Aa, 2Ab, 3A, 4A and 5A as in Seress (2012). If bound to <A>"NoAxioms"</A> then
  the algorithm only assumes the Majorana axioms M1 - M7. The default value is
  <A>"AllAxioms"</A>. </Item>
  <Mark><C>form</C></Mark>
  <Item> If this is bound to <A>true</A> then the algorithm assume the existence
  of an inner product (as in the definition of a Majorana algebra). Otherwise, if
  bound to <A>false</A> then no inner product is assumed (and we are in fact
  constructing an axial algebra that satisfies the Majorana fusion law).
  The default value is <A>true</A>.</Item>
  <Mark><C>embedding</C></Mark>
  <Item> If this is bound to <A>true</A> then the algorithm first attempts to construct
  large subalgebras of the final representation before starting the main construction.
  The default value is <A>false</A>.</Item>
 </List>
 </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


<Section Label="Chapter_Majorana_representations_Section_The_n-closed_function">
<Heading>The n-closed function</Heading>

<P/>
 A Majorana algebra <Math>V</Math> generated by a set of axes <Math>A</Math> is called <Math>n</Math>-closed if
 it is spanned as a vector space by products of elements of <Math>A</Math> of length at most <Math>n</Math>.
 As most known Majorana algebras are <Math>2</Math>-closed, the function <Ref Func="MajoranaRepresentation"/>
 only attempts to construct the <Math>2</Math>-closed part.
<P/>
 If it is not successful then the output is a partial Majorana representation,
 i.e. a Majorana representation with some missing algebra products.
 In this case, the function <Ref Func="MAJORANA_IsComplete"/>
 returns false.
<P/>
 If the user wishes, they may then pass this incomplete Majorana representation to the
 function <Ref Func="NClosedMajoranaRepresentation"/> in order to attempt construction
 of the <Math>3</Math>-closed part. This process may then be repeated as many times as the
 user wishes.
<ManSection>
  <Func Arg="rep" Name="NClosedMajoranaRepresentation" />
 <Description>
Takes as its input an incomplete Majorana representation rep that has been
 generated using the function <Ref Func="MajoranaRepresentation"/>. Again runs the
 main algorithm in order to attempt construction of the <Math>3</Math>-closed part of the algebra.
 If the function <Ref Func="NClosedMajoranaRepresentation"/> is called <Math>n</Math> times on the same
 Majorana representation rep then this representation will be the <Math>n + 2</Math>-closed part of the algebra.
 </Description>
</ManSection>


</Section>


</Chapter>

